{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In 1863, this person and James Montgomery led a successful raid on the Combahee River. This\nabolitionist was nicknamed by William Lloyd Garrison due to a similarity with a prophet in the Book\nof Exodus. This woman helped circumvent the Fugitive Slave Act by leading expeditions down the\nChesapeake coast of Maryland. For ten points, name this former slave, known as “Moses,” who guided\nmany escaped slaves to the North on the Underground Railroad.",
      "answer": [
        "Harriet Tubman",
        "Tubman"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In a myth about this location, the Devil threw a rock at a friar, creating the “Friar’s Heel” about 100\nfeet from a “Slaughter Stone.” William Stukeley hypothesized that this site was used as a Druid place of\nworship. The sunset of the winter solstice aligns with this site, which is located on the Salisbury plain.\nFor ten points, name this prehistoric monument of England, a ring of standing stones.",
      "answer": "Stonehenge"
    },
    {
      "question": "A type of music native to this country features the five-string vihuela and the deep-bodied, low-pitched\nguitarron. A folk song with an uneven five-four rhythm about a legless arthropod became popular during\nthis country’s revolution, with lyrics making fun of Victoriano Huerta sung by partisans of Pancho Villa.\nFor ten points, name this country where songs like “La Cucaracha” and “La Bamba” are played by\nmariachi bands south of the United States",
      "answer": [
        "Mexico",
        "United Mexican States",
        "Estados Unidos Mexicanos"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During his first Parliament, this man confiscated all the land holdings of his predecessor’s wife,\nElizabeth Woodville. Shortly after this man became king, the children Richard of Shrewsbury and\nEdward V mysteriously disappeared after being taken to the Tower of London. This man’s remains had\ndisappeared for centuries until, in 2012, they were found under a parking lot. For ten points, name this\nsubject of a Shakespeare history, the final king of the House of York.",
      "answer": "Richard III"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this event, John Indian was ordered to prepare a cake made of urine to feed to a dog. Cotton\nMather addressed a letter to the instigators of this event warning them against using “spectral evidence.”\nOne part of this event focused on the slave Tituba’s alleged spiritual influence over young children. Twenty\npeople died during the hysteria of, for ten points, what late 17th century tragedy in Massachusetts over\nsupposed evil magic?",
      "answer": "Salem witch trials"
    },
    {
      "question": "Immediately prior to this event, a character delivers a monologue in which he argues against a\npardon by stating “I am constant as the northern star.” A man justifies his involvement in this event by\ncomparing its central subject to a serpent’s egg. The target of this event is eulogized in a funeral oration\nthat begins “Friends, Romans, countrymen, lend me your ears.” For ten points, name this event in which\na Roman leader utters the dying words “Et tu, Brute.”",
      "answer": [
        "assassination of Julius Caesar",
        "Assassination of Caesar",
        "Murder of Julius Caesar",
        "Killing of Julius Caesar",
        "Stabbing of Julius Caesar",
        "Murder of Caesar",
        "Killing of Caesar",
        "Stabbing of Caesar"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One member of this program was given the call sign “Chaika,” or “Seagull,” and completed her\nintended action 48 times. The exclamation “poyekhali!” was made at the start of one of this program’s\nmissions; that mission, which began at the Baikonur Cosmodrome, was Vostok 1 and launched in 1961.\nValentina Tereshkova and Yuri Gagarin were members of, for ten points, what Cold War-era program\nthat, in 1957, launched Sputnik into orbit?",
      "answer": [
        "Soviet Union’s space program",
        "Soviet space",
        "Soviet space program",
        "Kosmicheskaya programma SSSR",
        "Russian space program",
        "Russia space",
        "Russia space program"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler overthrew the Chagatai Khanate after his capture of Balkh and defeated the leader of the\nGolden Horde, Tokhtamysh, at the Kur River. This man defeated the Tughluq Dynasty by setting camels\non fire to scare elephants. This ruler brought back the spoils from his sacks of Damascus and Delhi to his\ncapital of Samarkand. For ten points, name this Turkic conqueror of Central Asia who suffered from a\nlimp.",
      "answer": [
        "Timur the Lame",
        "Tamerlane",
        "Timur"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This politician used the slogan “in your guts you know he’s nuts” to mock his opponent’s campaign\nslogan; he also attacked that opponent with an advertisement featuring a girl picking at a daisy before\na nuclear explosion. This President signed amendments to Social Security that created Medicare and\nMedicaid, and he declared “War on Poverty” as part of his Great Society program. For ten points, name\nthis Texan US president who succeeded John F. Kennedy.",
      "answer": [
        "Lyndon Baines Johnson",
        "L Johnson",
        "Lyndon Johnson",
        "LBJ"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This politician attempted to stall the construction of the Hinckley nuclear power station out of fears\nof Chinese involvement. This figure was criticized after reportedly covering up the misfire of a Trident\nmissile in June 2016. She appointed the highly controversial Boris Johnson as Secretary of State for\nForeign Affairs, and in March 2017 she invoked Article 50 to formally begin the Brexit process. For ten\npoints, name this successor of David Cameron as prime minister of the United Kingdom.",
      "answer": [
        "Theresa May",
        "May"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) Abraham Lincoln was assassinated by what stage actor in 1865?",
      "answer": [
        "John Wilkes Booth",
        "Booth"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A building featuring a coffered one of these structures was originally commissioned by Marcus Agrippa\nand renovated by Hadrian. Constantino Brumidi decorated the interior surface of one of these structures\nwith murals that can be seen from the rotunda below. An oculus allows light to shine into the Pantheon\nthrough, for ten points, what architectural feature that serves as the roof of the United States Capitol\nbuilding?",
        "answer": "domes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The murals in the inside of the Capitol rotunda show the Apotheosis of this leader, who was\nalso shown being crowned by fame and peace in a relief sculpture on an exterior wall.",
        "answer": [
          "George Washington",
          "Washington"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A civil war during this conflict was fought between the Armagnacs and Burgundians. One side of\nthis war sent out cavalry raids called chevauch´ees [sheh-voh-SHAYS], sometimes led by the Black Prince.\nCharles VII was crowned after this war’s Siege of Orleans was lifted. Longbows helped the English win\nthe Battle of Crecy during, for ten points, what war between England and France that lasted from 1337\nto 1453?",
        "answer": [
          "Hundred Years’ War",
          "Hundred Years’"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Siege of Orleans was lifted with the help of this 17-year-old French peasant girl. She was\ncaptured and burned at the stake by the English, but cleared by the Pope years later and made a saint in\n1920.",
        "answer": [
          "Saint Joan of Arc",
          "Joan of Arc",
          "Saint Jeanne d'Arc",
          "Jeanne d'Arc"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A treaty negotiated by this man and Colonel Edward House was targeted for change by the Lodge\nReservations. Before becoming the Governor of New Jersey, this politician served as Princeton University’s\npresident. This President asked Congress for a declaration of war after news of the Zimmermann Telegram\nbroke. For ten points, name this US President who failed in his promise to “keep us out of” World War I.",
        "answer": [
          "Thomas Woodrow Wilson",
          "Woodrow Wilson",
          "Wilson"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Henry Cabot Lodge’s Reservations concerned the US’s obligations as part of this body. The\nLodge Reservations were voted down by the Senate shortly before the Treaty of Versailles was voted down,\nso the US never joined this organization.",
        "answer": "League of Nations"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this man’s reign, his brother’s general Kitbuqa lost the Battle of Ain Jalut, the first time his\nempire’s army had been halted entirely. This man defeated Ariq Boke in the Toluid civil war before being\nnamed Khan. This man’s invasions of Japan were twice halted by the kamikaze winds. For ten points,\nname this founder of the Yuan Dynasty, a Mongol leader who was the grandson of Genghis Khan.",
        "answer": [
          "Kublai Khan",
          "Kublai"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Kublai Khan established the Yuan Dynasty’s capital at Dadu, which is now this city. This city\nwas known as Zhongdu as the capital of the Greater Jin Dynasty, and as Peking while capital of the Qing\n[ching] Dynasty.",
        "answer": "Beijing"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This scientist described the “chemistry of the imponderable” in a Nobel Prize lecture explaining the\nwork of Henri Becquerel. This scientist co-authored a study comparing tumor cell and healthy cell death\nrates when exposed to an element that this chemist isolated in 1910, four years after the death of her\nhusband Pierre. The first woman to win a Nobel Prize was, for ten points, what Polish-French physicist\nwho discovered radium while studying radioactive decay?",
        "answer": [
          "Marie Sklodowska Curie",
          "Marie Curie",
          "Marie Sklodowska",
          "Sklodowska",
          "Curie"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Marie Curie isolated radium from a sample of radium chloride via a cathode of this element;\nthe radium reacted with this element to form an amalgam. This element, which is a liquid at room\ntemperature, has largely been phased out of use in scientific thermometers.",
        "answer": [
          "mercury",
          "Hg"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This kingdom allowed Janos Hunyadi to serve as regent despite losing at the Battle of Varna. The\nethnic group that founded this kingdom raided Europe before their defeat by Holy Roman Emperor\nOtto I at Lechfeld and are known as the Magyars. This kingdom came into personal unions with nearby\nCroatia, Austria, and Bohemia and is surrounded by the Carpathian Mountains. For ten points, name\nthis kingdom that ruled from what is now Budapest.",
        "answer": [
          "Kingdom of Hungary",
          "Hungary"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hungary was eventually split by the Habsburgs, the Ottomans, and this third independent state\nruled by John Zapolya. Bram Stoker’s Count Dracula came from this region.",
        "answer": "Transylvania"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Bradford Washburn, the first person to climb the West Buttress route on this mountain, was married\nto Barbara Polk, the first woman to climb this mountain. Walter Harper, a member of the Koyukon\ntribe, was the first to climb this mountain in 1913. President Obama’s 2015 executive order renaming this\nmountain was supported by Lisa Murkowski and denounced by Ohio politicians. For ten points, name this\nhighest mountain in North America, formerly named for a U.S. President.",
        "answer": [
          "Denali",
          "Mount McKinley",
          "McKinley"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another Alaskan feature is this island chain that forms a namesake “Arc” to the southwest. This\nchain’s islands of Attu and Kiska were invaded by the Japanese in World War II.",
        "answer": [
          "Aleutian Islands",
          "Aleutian"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "George Carteret was given land in North Carolina and what is now this state by Charles II. The\nLoyalist William Franklin, son of Ben Franklin, governed this colony until the Revolution. In 1937, a dire\nradio report from this state noted flames “four or five hundred feet into the sky...Oh, the humanity!”\nThomas Edison’s Menlo Park labs were in, for ten points, what Atlantic coast state whose industrial cities\ninclude Newark and Trenton?",
        "answer": "New Jersey"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned 1937 radio report, including the cry “Oh, the humanity!”, detailed the fiery\ncrash of this German zeppelin.",
        "answer": [
          "LZ 129 Hindenburg",
          "Hindenburg"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "AMERICAN NATIONAL SYMBOLS",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Man who declares “I want you” in James Flagg’s US Army recruitment posters.",
          "answer": "Uncle Sam"
        },
        {
          "question": "Philadelphia woman whose credit for making the first American flag has been questioned by modern\nhistorians.",
          "answer": [
            "Betsy Ross",
            "Ross"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "National bird, found on the Presidential seal, whose selection as a symbol was opposed by Ben\nFranklin.",
          "answer": "bald eagle"
        },
        {
          "question": "Four-word phrase that was adopted as the US motto and placed on American paper money during\nthe Cold War.",
          "answer": "In God We Trust"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fort whose bombing inspired “The Star-Spangled Banner.”",
          "answer": [
            "Fort McHenry",
            "McHenry"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "World War II icon of women factory workers, commonly associated with the “We Can Do It!” poster.",
          "answer": "Rosie the Riveter"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sousa song named the National March in 1987.",
          "answer": "The Stars and Stripes Forever"
        },
        {
          "question": "Action whose legality was debated in Texas v. Johnson.",
          "answer": "burning the American flag"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Name the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "CASTLES",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Protective ditch, usually filled with water, surrounding many castles.",
          "answer": "moats"
        },
        {
          "question": "System of government that lent itself to castle-building, as relatively independent lords ruled over\ntheir lands from a castle and served a king.",
          "answer": [
            "feudalism",
            "feudal",
            "feudalist"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Siege engines that used a counterweight to swing a projectile at castle walls.",
          "answer": "trebuchets"
        },
        {
          "question": "Chinese technological innovation that allowed for bombards and mortars, making castles largely\nobsolete by the 15th century.",
          "answer": "gunpowder"
        },
        {
          "question": "Castle built by William the Conqueror outside of London after his conquest of England. It is now a\nroyal residence.",
          "answer": [
            "Windsor Castle",
            "Windsor"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "“Mad” King of Bavaria who built Neuschwanstein [noysh-van-stein] Castle.",
          "answer": [
            "Ludwig II",
            "Ludwig"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Coastal region of France east of Brittany where motte-and-bailey castles were first developed.",
          "answer": "Normandy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crusading group that occupied Krak des Chevaliers [she-vahl-yay] in Syria until 1271 before going to\nMalta.",
          "answer": [
            "Knights Hospitaller",
            "Hospitaller",
            "the Order of Knights of the Hospital of Saint John",
            "the Order of Knights of the Hospital of Saint John of Jerusalem",
            "the order of Hospitallers"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Name the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "NEW WORLD PIRACY",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Items displayed on the classic “Jolly Roger” pirate flag.",
          "answer": [
            "bones",
            "skull",
            "crossbones",
            "skull and crossbones",
            "skull and bones"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Alcoholic beverage made from distilled sugarcane juice that pirates drank mixed with water as\n“bumbo” or “grog.”",
          "answer": "rum"
        },
        {
          "question": "Disease caused by a lack of Vitamin C that pirates could avoid by eating limes.",
          "answer": "scurvy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sea dominated by 17th century pirates from Cuba to the Lesser Antilles to South America.",
          "answer": [
            "Caribbean Sea",
            "Caribbean"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Island in that sea where pirates docked at Port Royal. It’s now a country with capital Kingston.",
          "answer": "Jamaica"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pirate who commanded the Queen Anne’s Revenge and died in a shootout in North Carolina.",
          "answer": [
            "Blackbeard",
            "Edward Teach",
            "Teach",
            "Edward Thatch",
            "Thatch"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Pirate who captured the Quedagh Merchant and supposedly left a massive buried treasure, according\nto Robert Louis Stevenson and others.",
          "answer": [
            "Captain William Kidd",
            "Kidd"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Famous pirate island just north of Haiti, where Henry Morgan hired some of his crew. A “Dry” island\ngroup off the Florida Keys shares its name.",
          "answer": [
            "Tortuga",
            "Dry Tortugas"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Name the..."
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This company spent 11 months in bankruptcy protection after three years of\nmismanagement by former ESPN executive Mark Shapiro and NFL owner Dan Snyder.\nIn 2005, this company closed AstroWorld in Houston and, due to Hurricane (20 pts) ",
        "Katrina,\nits New Orleans facility. In 2017, this company stopped promoting the “Stars and Bars”\nConfederate symbol at its primary (10 pts) ",
        "“Over Texas” location. For ten points, name this American\nchain of amusement parks whose name refers to the number of nations that have governed Texas."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Six Flags Entertainment Corporation",
        "Six Flags"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A prominent port on this body of water was once ruled by a zamorin and was the most\ndominant city on the Malabar Coast. During the Ming Dynasty, Zheng He asserted Chinese\ndominance over (20 pts) ",
        "trade routes in and around this ocean. To reach Calicut, Vasco da\nGama rounded the Cape of (10 pts) ",
        "Good Hope and sailed along and across this body of water. The\nendpoint of the Brahmaputra and Ganges rivers is, for ten points, what South Asian ocean between Africa\nand Australia?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Indian Ocean",
        "Indian",
        "Arabian Sea",
        "Arabian"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This general dislodged his opponents from Gaines’s Mill after the wounding of Joseph\nJohnston at Seven Pines allowed him to take command; that victory was part of this\ngeneral’s Seven Days Battles against George (20 pts) ",
        "McClellan. Because this man’s family\nhome stood across the Potomac River overlooking the capital, the government seized it and\nbuilt (10 pts) ",
        "Arlington National Cemetery on its grounds. For ten points, name this man who commanded\nthe Army of Northern Virginia and surrendered at Appomattox Court House, ending the Civil War."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Robert Edward Lee",
        "Robert Lee",
        "Robert E. Lee",
        "Lee"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Early in this monarch’s reign, the Earl of Bute was employed as prime minister. Newgate\nPrison burned down during the reign of this monarch, who also faced the Gordon Riots.\nGeorge Grenville worked under this monarch, who barred expansion west of the (20 pts) ",
        "Appalachians. Lord North passed the Townshend Acts and the (10 pts) ",
        "Intolerable Acts while\nserving, for ten points, what English king who rejected the Olive Branch Petition.and lost control over\nthe colonies in the American Revolution?"
      ],
      "answer": "George III"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Anti-British activists of this religion in the early-20th century were known as “LalBal-Pal.” A speech beginning “sisters and brothers of America” introduced this religion\nto America at the 1893 Parliament of the World’s Religions and was given by (20 pts) ",
        "Swami\nVivekananda. A liberation from the birth-rebirth cycle sought in this religion is known\nas moksha. Opposition to this religion’s (10 pts) ",
        "Brahmanist caste system led to the development of\nJainism and Buddhism. For ten points, name this predominant religion of India."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Hinduism",
        "Hindu"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man faced off against Royalists under Miguel de la Torre in a crucial 1821 battle.\nThis man, who assumed control of the armies of the United Provinces after issuing the\nCartagena Manifesto, sanctioned indiscriminate killing by his forces in the (20 pts) ",
        "Decree of\nWar to the Death. After winning the Battle of Carabobo, this leader presided over the\nfounding of Gran (10 pts) ",
        "Colombia. For ten points, name this Venezuelan independence fighter who\nliberated large areas of South America and is the namesake of a South American country."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Simon Bolivar",
        "Bolivar",
        "Simon Jose Antonio de la Santisima Trinidad de Bolivar y Palacios"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This government’s attempt to unify Protestantism was opposed by Dietrich Bonhoeffer’s\nConfessing Church. The Red Orchestra and White Rose groups opposed this government,\nwhich attacked modernist art at the (20 pts) ",
        "Degenerate Art Exhibition. Leni Riefenstahl’s film\nTriumph of the Will was produced with the help of Joseph (10 pts) ",
        "Goebbels, this government’s\npropaganda minister. For ten points, name this regime that created the Nuremberg Laws to persecute\nJews before engineering the Holocaust."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Nazi Germany",
        "Nazi",
        "Germany",
        "National Socialist German Workers’ Party",
        "NSGWP",
        "the Third Reich"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this time period, a hunger march called the Jarrow Crusade marched to London,\nwhere the House of Commons completely ignored them. In this time period, Francis\nTownsend proposed a two-percent transaction tax to fund an (20 pts) ",
        "Old Age Revolving\nPension Plan. The Smoot Hawley Act may have worsened the effects of this time period, in\nwhich vagrants were arrested for (10 pts) ",
        "“riding the rails” and living in Hoovervilles. For ten points,\nname this period of history that followed the 1929 Wall Street Crash and adversely affected economies\naround the world."
      ],
      "answer": "Great Depression"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) John Glover defended this city from attack at Pell’s Point after the enemy landed\nat Throg’s Neck. In this city, loyalists helped William Howe’s men bypass Jamaica\nPass. Continental Army officers gave farewells in this city’s (20 pts) ",
        "Fraunces Tavern\nafter a British occupation that lasted until 1783. Fort Washington stands in this\nmodern-day city, which is connected to Fort (10 pts) ",
        "Lee in the New Jersey Palisades by the\nGeorge Washington Bridge. The Battle of Long Island occurred in, for ten points, what city that\nis composed of five boroughs?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "New York City",
        "New York",
        "NYC"
      ]
    }
  ]
}